Guide to the Magee Family Papers, 1790-1952 DAR.1968.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Magee Family Papers
1790-1952
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Magee family
DAR.1968.01
26.77 Linear Feet (32 boxes manuscript material and 19 boxes photographic material)
This collection of correspondence, land plot drawings, receipts and photographs records the lives of prominent Pittsburgh citizens Judge Christopher Magee and his wife Elizabeth, and their children, Jane, Walter, and Christopher Magee, Jr. The Magee Family Papers document land development undertaken by the Magee and Watson families in Pittsburgh from the 1790s to the 1890s. Also present are Watson family papers relating to land sales and development conducted by Christopher's mother, Jane Watson, grandfather Andrew Watson, Jr., and uncle Robert Watson.
Biography
The Magee and Watson families were among the early settlers and developers of Pittsburgh. In the early nineteenth century, they were joined by the marriage of hatter Christopher Linem Magee (1786-1839) and Jane Watson (1796- 1880). The Watson family purchased and developed land in Pittsburgh, leasing lots to relations in the Wylie and Black families, as well as other neighbors. Jane and Christopher Magee had four children, including Christopher (1829-1909).
Christopher graduated from the Western University of Pennsylvania, where his uncle, Robert Watson, had been chancellor, with a bachelor's degree in 1848. Later, he earned his law degree from the University of Pennsylvania in 1852. He was elected to the state legislature in 1856.
In 1859 Christopher married his cousin, Elizabeth Louise McLeod (1836-1902) of Staten Island, New York, and they resided on Grant Street in Pittsburgh. Elizabeth Louise, known to her family as Louisa, made extended trips to the east coast to visit her family throughout her marriage to Christopher. Later in life, she summered in Jacksonville, Florida, and various resorts in New Jersey and New York.
Christopher and Louisa had seven children, five of whom lived to adulthood: Margaret (1861-1894), Christopher, Jr. (1863-1951), Jane (1869-1880), Julia (1871-1921) and Walter (1874-1952). Margaret was survived by her husband, Kier Mitchell, and daughter, Louise. Louise attended Misses Shipley's School in Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, with the financial assistance of her grandfather. Christopher, Jr. earned his law degree from the University of Pennsylvania and was employed by a Pittsburgh firm. Walter, called "Doc" by his siblings, traveled extensively in Europe and Asia. Little about Margaret, Jane or Julia is found in this collection or in secondary sources.
Christopher Magee was appointed to the Court of Common Pleas No. 2 of Allegheny County in 1885. He was active in the community as an incorporator of Shadyside Academy, Pittsburgh Hospital for Children, and the Allegheny Cemetery. He was a member of the Academy of Arts and Sciences, the Pittsburgh Chamber of Commerce, the University Club of Pittsburgh, the Delta Phi Club of New York City and the Pennsylvania Forestry Association. Christopher was involved in the Democratic Party, serving on the Allegheny County Finances Committee.
The extended Magee family had prominent members not mentioned in this collection. For example, William A. Magee, mayor of Pittsburgh, was a cousin of Judge Christopher Magee. Also, Christopher Lyman Magee (1848-1901), was a Republican Party political leader in Pittsburgh whose home became the maternity hospital that is now UPMC Magee Women's Hospital.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection of photographs and manuscripts relate to the nuclear and extended family of Christopher and Louisa Magee. There is a great deal of family correspondence, most notably letters between Christopher and Louisa from their courtship and marriage in the 1850s until her death in 1902. Louisa also received many letters from her family in New York state, including letters from her Aunt Sue (whose last name is not indicated in the letters), and her father, Reverend John M. McLeod.
The collection also contains letters from their sons, Walter and Christopher, Jr., and their granddaughter, Louise. Christopher, Jr. corresponded with his mother during her various trips to New York, and Walter sent his father many letters from his travels abroad. Louisa also received letters from her relations in the Wylie family. Most of these letters relate to the health, work and travel of family members. Financial issues are sometimes mentioned. Some of the letters document a major family outing to the 1893 Chicago World's Fair, attended by Louisa, her son Walter, her sister-in-law Jane, and her granddaughter Louise.
In addition to family correspondence, a small group of letters and mailings related to Christopher's mother, Jane Watson Magee, can be found in this collection. Stock certificates in the Algonquin Company, a Montana mining operation, and the Coal Hill Military Co. are present.
The collection also contains extensive handwritten notes on cases argued by Christopher early in his career, and cases he heard as judge of the Court of Common Pleas. The collection includes the certificate of Judge Magee's appointment to the Court of Common Pleas No. 2 of the Fifth Judicial District in 1885, as well as his legal degree, and that of his son, Christopher, Jr., from the University of Pennsylvania.
Extensive receipts document the purchase of household goods, utilities and payment of taxes and insurance. Many of these materials are undated and fragmentary, although it is clear that they relate to Magee and Watson family purchases from the late eighteenth through the early nineteenth century. A substantial portion of the receipts from both the Watson and Magee families relate to domestic purchases, including food, utilities, clothing, and household goods.
The collection contains materials on land development in Pittsburgh, including large land plot diagrams related to the properties of Andrew Watson in the late 1700s and of Robert Watson and his sister Jane in the 1800s. Indentures and maps of Andrew Watson and Robert Watson's properties, land sales and leases from 1828 to 1881 are in the collection. The papers of Andrew Watson include a 1796 license issued by Thomas Mifflin to open a Public House, and the certificate of his appointment as Justice of the Peace in 1798. Additional Watson family papers relating to land sales were collected by the Darlington family as the Hugh Henry Brackenridge and Andrew Watson Papers, 1784-1827 (see Related Materials).
The collection also contains non-manuscript items, including a family bible, a scrapbook of newspaper clippings about the early years of flight, and pairs of spectacles. It is unclear to which family member these items belonged. A number of photographic formats are present, and multiple large photo albums in which family members are identified, including Jane Watson Magee, Judge Christopher Magee, Walter Pollack Magee, Elizabeth Louise McLeod Magee, and other family members.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged by creator and format. The Magee and Watson family papers have been arranged in separate series.
Series I. Magee Family Papers, 1798-1952
Series II. Watson Family Papers, 1795-1901
Series III. Receipts, 1790-1910
Series IV. Family Material, Oversized, 1791-1906
Series V. Photographic Materials, 1850-1915
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Louise McLeod Mitchell and Geoffry Conklin to the Darlington Memorial Library in 1968.
Previous Citation
Magee Family Papers, 1790-1952, DAR.1968.01, Darlington Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Hugh Henry Brackenridge and Andrew Watson Papers, 1784-1827, DAR.1937.04, Darlington Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Separated Material
Large manuscript materials, such as maps and other diagrams, are stored separately in flat cases to accommodate their size. Bound materials, including scrapbooks and ledgers, are also stored separately from manuscripts. These materials are indicated as "Oversize" throughout the finding aid.
Custodial History
This collection was located in the Darlington Memorial Library in the University's Cathedral of Learning until 2007 when it was moved to the ULS Archives Service Center for processing, storage, preservation and service. However, it remains in the custodianship of the ULS Special Collections Department.
Real estate developers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Judges -- Pennsylvania; Lawyers -- Pennsylvania; Legal documents; Correspondence; Receipts (Financial records); Photographs; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Real estate development -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Family papers; Pittsburgh Junction Railroad Company; Coal Hill Military Company; Algonquin Company; Shadyside Presbyterian Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Bellefield Club (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Watson, Robert; Watson, Andrew; Magee, Christopher; Magee, Elizabeth Louise; Magee, Christopher; Magee, Jane (Watson); Magee, Christopher L.; Watson family; Magee family
- Magee Family Papers, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains the papers of Christopher and Louisa McLeod Magee, their son, Walter, and the papers of extended family members. The materials encompass family correspondence, financial documents, land plots, and papers from Christopher's legal career. Highlights of this series include materials related to a family trip to the 1893 Chicago World's Fair, stock and correspondence of the silver mining Algonquin Co. of Montana, and estate documents.
  - Elizabeth and Christopher Magee, 1817-1908; 1.
    Scope and Contents note
    This correspondence is largely between Christopher and Louisa from the 1850s until Louisa's death in 1902. The letters discuss domestic matters, particularly the lives of their children, and are often warm and politely romantic.
    Correspondence to Louisa from her father, Reverend John M. McLeod of New York, her brothers, Rutgers and Alexander, and her Aunt Sue often inquires about her children and health, and shares family news. Christopher received letters from Walter during his travels abroad. This subseries also includes Elizabeth and Christopher's 1859 marriage certificate, Christopher's memberships to the Bellefield Club and the National Geographic Society, an architectural drawing by J. W. Kerr of a summer house, and Louisa's estate papers. Ephemera and newspaper clippings relate to literature and poetry collected from print sources.
    - Correspondence, 1817-1858 (Box 1, Folder 1-19)
    - Correspondence, 1859-1864 (Box 2, Folder 1-11)
    - Correspondence, 1865-1885 (Box 3, Folder 1-21)
    - Correspondence, 1886-1895 (Box 4, Folder 1-11)
    - Correspondence, 1896-1901 (Box 5, Folder 1-10)
    - Correspondence, 1901-1908 (Box 6, Folder 1-10)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
    - Henry Baldwin to Christopher Magee, 1827 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Address to electors of Allegheny County, 1833 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - John A. Parkinson to Christopher Magee, 1855 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Marriage Certificate, January 12, 1859 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Algonquin Company, 1876-1881 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Christopher Magee, membership at the Bellefield Club, 1889-1903 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Chicago Worlds Fair, 1893 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Christopher Magee Pennsylvania Forestry Association membership, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Christopher Magee National Geographic membership certificate, April 21, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Elizabeth Louise McLeod Magee Estate, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - In Memoriam Hon. Christopher Magee, booklet, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Stock, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Receipts, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Receipts, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Printed ephemera, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Printed ephemera, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Printed ephemera, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Shadyside Presbyterian, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Envelopes, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Christopher Magee Legal Papers, 1856-1903; 2.
    Handwritten notes of Christopher Magee, during his time as an attorney from 1856 through his appointment to the Court of Common Pleas in 1885, are found in this subseries. These papers indicate that he still worked as an attorney during his 1856 tenure in the state legislature. The legal notes in this collection are handwritten, and seem to have been for personal use; they list the date and title of the case, and may be drafts of briefs. The subseries contains business letters from James Negley, John A. Parkinson and Henry Baldwin, Jr. Additionally, the law degrees of both Christopher Jr. and Sr. from the University of Pennsylvania are present; these degrees, including dates, are in Latin. Certificates of Christopher Magee's temporary appointment and subsequent election to the Court of Common Pleas No. 2 of the Fifth Judicial District of Allegheny County are also present.
    - Legal notes, 1856-1888 (Box 9, Folder 1-11)
    - Legal notes, 1888-1889 (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
    - Legal notes, 1889-1891 (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
    - Legal notes, 1891-1894 (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
    - Legal notes, 1895-1903, undated (Box 13, Folder 1-7)
    - Legal notes, undated (Box 14, Folder 1-8)
    - Legal notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 1-6)
    - Receipt of payment to Robert Carothers, July 3, 1826 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Henry Baldwin, Jr. to Christopher Magee, April 25 1827 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Henry Baldwin, Jr. to Christopher Magee, January 2, 1828 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - John A. Parkinson to Christopher Magee, 1855 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Pennsylvanian, July 19, 1856 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - James Negley to Christopher Magee, July 1, 1859 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Christopher Magee Law License, 1862 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Casebooks, 1880-1891 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Pittsburgh Junction Railroad Case, 1882 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - William Searhart to Unknown, July 3, 1891 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - William L. Campbell to Christopher Magee, January 19, 1892 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Christopher Magee to James Galbreach, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Ladies Aid Society of Bloomfield to Christopher Magee, undated (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Casebooks, 1887 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Paperbooks, 1889 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Allegheny Company notice, 1891 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Samuel McCamant to Christopher Magee, February 1, 1892 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - T.B. Patton to Christopher Magee, February 2, 1892 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - William Yost to Christopher Magee, May 9, 1895 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Legal catalog, undated (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - A & A.M. Blakely Law Office notice, undated (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Clipping, undated (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Record of Clerk of Courts, undated (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Petition, undated (Box 16, Folder 24)
  - Personal Papers of Walter Pollack Magee, 1894-1952; 3.
    This subseries contains correspondence and ephemera. While Walter resided on Diamond Street in Pittsburgh he held memberships to the Pittsburgh Golf Club and the White Marsh Valley Hunt Club, and applied to the American Committee for a Devastated France during the First World War. Walter's received correspondence documents his extensive world travels, including visits to Egypt, Italy, Greece, England, France, Hawaii, Japan, and Burma in the early 1900s. Letters from his parents, siblings and his niece, Louise, indicate a strong relationship with his family. A variety of postcards from friends abroad have photographs with ethnographic and erotic themes. Series IV contains images of Walter throughout his life, including many photographs taken while he was in college. One such notable photograph shows Walter and a classmate dressed in women's clothing, likely as part of a college prank. The series contains a description of Walter's estate, and the design image for his headstone.
    - Correspondence, 1894-1914 (Box 17, Folder 1-15)
    - Correspondence, 1915-1926, undated (Box 18, Folder 1-14)
    - Open letter, RMS India, 1893 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Printed Ephemera, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Memberships, 1916-1917 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Travel itinerary, 1908 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Estate, 1952 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Bills, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Bills, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Bills and receipts, undated (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Compositions, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Extended Family Papers, 1798-1901; 4.
    Included are Louise's correspondence from her father, Kier Mitchell and grandfather, Christopher Magee, as well as her report cards from Miss Gleim's School for Girls in Pittsburgh in 1905. Also present are the 1798 citizenship papers of Christopher's Irish-born paternal grandfather, Robert Magee, and the 1880 will of Norman McLeod Magee. Various wills, letters and ephemera are included.
    - Robert Magee Citizenship Papers, May 12, 1798 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Discharge papers, Hugh Huiphan, 1815 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Matthew J. Magee Law certificate, 1818 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Proceedings of Freemasons, Edwardsville Chicago, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Sir to Charles Bradford, 1832 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Dick John to William Pentland, April 30, 1841 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - David Dick to James R. Dick, February 1839 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Family Correspondence, 1861-1910 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Sir to Sister, 1862 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Sir to William Pentland, 1866 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Drawings, Norman McLeod Magee, February 1880 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Margaret McLeod Magee Correspondence, 1880 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Will of John Niel McLeod, undated (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Elizabeth Louise McLeod Mitchell papers, 1893-1901 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Thomas Mumford, Will, 1896 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Sir to G. W. Roberts, 1900 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - Louise Mitchell to Sue, 1916 (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - Indenture, undated (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - Unknown to Margaret, undated (Box 20, Folder 19)
    - Frances Carr to Lucianda Hite, undated (Box 20, Folder 20)
    - Sir to Mrs. Wylie, undated (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Estate of Ann McKinney, undated (Box 20, Folder 22)
    - Sir to Platt Hubbard, undated (Box 20, Folder 23)
    - Mamma to Norman Magee, undated (Box 20, Folder 24)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Kier Mitchell correspondence, undated (Box 20, Folder 25)
- Watson Family Papers, 1795-1901; II.
  This series contains papers of Jane Magee, her father Andrew Watson, and her brother Robert Watson, relating to their properties in Pittsburgh. Jane's papers also relate to her estate.
  - Andrew and Robert Watson Papers, 1795-1901; 1.
    Andrew Watson's 1796 license to open a public house and the 1798 certificate appointing him Justice of the Peace indicate his active public life in early Pittsburgh. The collection also contains professional information about his son, Robert, including his admission to the bar of Allegheny County by William Wilkins and Alexander Brackenridge. Robert lived in the sixth ward of Pittsburgh and traveled to France in 1849 and Germany in 1865.
    This subseries includes correspondence, drawings of land plots, indentures and leases related to properties owned and developed by Andrew Watson, and his son, Robert Watson. The collection includes Andrew Watson's land deeds and indentures with William Finley, John Reed and John Wilkins, and diagrams of his partial holdings. Robert's land holdings near Market Street, Chestnut Street, Bluff Street and Second Street are part of the 1848 partition of land annexed to the city of Pittsburgh; this map also shows the holdings of his neighbors, including the J. B. Wylie, Jane Magee, and members of the Black and McClelland families. A similar, though undated, map of Public Road shows plots owned by Watson, Magee, and Black family members, as well as those of William Pentland and James Ross.
    The Watson papers show the family's interest in its own genealogy, particularly a list of family names and relationships that unfortunately lacks birth, death or marriage dates. This record focuses on the extended Watson family, but documents very little of the Magee family. A journal written by Robert Watson also describes the family genealogy. Some of the legal papers indicate that the Watsons were related in business and by blood to the Black and Wylie families of Pittsburgh. For additional information on the Watson family, see the Hugh Henry Brackenridge and Andrew Watson Papers, 1784-1827, also held by the Darlington Memorial Library.
    - Andrew Watson correspondence, 1795-1842 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Andrew Watson, will, September 17, 1822 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - William Alexander, reciept for county taxes from Watson brothers, December 28 1826 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Robert Watson, Pittsburgh Farmers & Mechanics Turnpike Road Co., 1835-1856 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Robert Watson correspondence, 1842-1863 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Andrew Watson insurance policies, 1843-1861 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - John McLeod to Robert Watson, 1849-1850 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Robert Watson, House of Refuge contribution, 1857 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Robert Watson, travel to France, 1865 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Robert Watson, will, 1875 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Will of Jane Black, 1901 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Robert Watson receipts, undated (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Robert Watson receipts, undated (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Robert Watson journal, undated (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Watson family genealogy, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Diagram of calculating machine, undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Mathematics notes, undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Land plots, undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Legal papers, 1828 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Legal papers, 1821-1827 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Legal papers, 1829-1830 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Legal papers, 1831-1833 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Legal papers, 1835-1840 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Legal papers, 1841-1845 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Legal papers, 1846-1850 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Legal papers, 1851-1855 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Legal papers, 1856-1860 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Legal papers, 1861-1870 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Legal papers, 1871-1880 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Legal papers, 1881 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Personal Papers of Jane Watson Magee, 1847-1880; 2.
    This subseries relates in large part to the estate of Jane Magee, including diagrams of her properties and documentation of their collective value at the time of her death. Little is known of Jane's husband, Christopher, but a document in this subseries shows that he served as executor to the estate of William Diehl in the matter of James R. Irwin's mortgage. Correspondence to Jane shows her close relationship with Christopher and other family members.
    - Correspondence, 1847-1880 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1847-1880 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1847-1880 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1847-1880 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - First Presbyterian Church, undated (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Family Plots at Allegheny Cemetery, undated (Box 26, Folder 6)